<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Churches paradox or the substance of a sermon preached at the place of Cumbusnethen in a barn, in the parish of Cumbusnethen in Clydsdale. By Mr. John Welsh.</title>
            <author>Welch, John, ca. 1624-1681.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1710</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65420</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1310B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC T166345</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99834201</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99834201</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38699</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65420)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38699)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2103:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Churches paradox or the substance of a sermon preached at the place of Cumbusnethen in a barn, in the parish of Cumbusnethen in Clydsdale. By Mr. John Welsh.</title>
                  <author>Welch, John, ca. 1624-1681.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>22p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh?,</pubPlace>
                  <date>1710?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:38699:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Churches PARADOX: OR THE SUBSTANCE OF A SERMON PREACHED at the Place of <hi>Cumbuſnethen</hi> in a Barn, in the Pariſh of <hi>Cumbuſnethen</hi> in <hi>Clydſdale.</hi> By Mr. <hi>John Welſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Zechariah 14 Chap. 6. and 7. Verſes.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And it ſhall come to paſs in that day, that the Light ſhall not be clear, nor dark. But it ſhall be one day which ſhall be known to the Lord, not day, nor night: but it ſhall come to paſs that at evening time it ſhall be light.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:38699:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:38699:2"/>
            <head>THE TEXT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Zechariah 14. Chap. 6. and 7. Verſes.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And it ſhall come to paſs in that Day, that the Light ſhall not be clear nor dark. But it ſhall be one day which ſhall be known to the LORD, not Day nor Night: but it ſhall come to paſs that at evening time it ſhall be Light.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THere is divers Caſes that befalls the Church, while ſhe is Militant here upon Earth; Sometimes She ſhines, and is very <hi>bright as the Sun, clear as the Moon, ſtrong as an Army with Banners:</hi> Sometimes again, She is like dark Night; She is under very great dark Clouds, <hi>She walketh in Darkneſs, and hath no Light,</hi> as it is in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 50.10. But there is ſometimes alſo that ſhe is in a Caſe different from both theſe, and that is, ſhe hath ſome Light, and ſome Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in her Caſe, ſo that it can neither be ſaid, that ſhe altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Shines, nor yet that ſhe is altogether in Darkneſs. This is the Caſe that <hi>Zechariah</hi> here ſpeaks of at this time in this place: If the Light ſhould neither be Clear nor Dark, neither altogether ſo clear as to be called Noon-tide of the Day; nor yet altogether ſo Dark as to be called Mid-night with her: But how then? but like the Evening-tide, a little after the Sun ſett, before the Night come on, there ſhould be ſome Light and ſome Darkneſs in her Caſe. A mixt Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of Wrath and Mercy ſhould be letten out upon the Kirk
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38699:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>And there is ſome comfortable things promiſed to the <hi>Kirk,</hi> while ſhe is in this Caſe. And <hi>Firſt,</hi> It is promiſed to her, that this her ſad Caſe ſhall be but for <hi>one day;</hi> that is, but a wie while, a very ſhort time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is promiſed to the <hi>Kirk,</hi> that at Even, it ſhall be Light; that is, when there is greateſt appearance of ſader and darker Night, then immediatly the LORD ſhall cauſe <hi>the Day Spring from on High to ariſe upon the Kirk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now from theſe we ſhall ſpeak but to Three or Four Things by way of <hi>Doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the <hi>Firſt</hi> Thing we ſee from the Words is this, That ſometimes the LORDs Diſpenſations with the Kirk is ſuch, that they can neither be ſaid to be Dark nor Clear, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like Night nor like Day; but ſomewhat of Light, and ſomewhat of Darkneſs in the Diſpenſation; Somewhat of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſomewhat of Mercy may be the Caſe of the <hi>Kirk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> A ſecond Thing we notice of this, That the time of the <hi>Kirks</hi> Trouble though ſometimes the LORD is pleaſed to lengthen, and to make it long; yet ſometimes alſo, as it is here, it ſhall be but a ſhort while, and but for <hi>one day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That the <hi>Kirks</hi> Trouble though it be but for a ſhort time, and but for <hi>one day,</hi> and no body kens when it will end: Yet for the Comfort of the <hi>Kirk, it is a day known to the LORD,</hi> though neither Enemies nor Friends kens when the Day of Delivery will come, <hi>yet it is a day known to the LORD:</hi> It is a limited time that GOD hath ſet the bounds off.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> That when the <hi>Kirk</hi> in all appearance and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability looks like a thicker and blacker darkneſs and greater Deſolations, then very ſhortly the LORD will make Light to ariſe, and the <hi>Day Spring from on High to ariſe upon the</hi> Kirk, even at the evening, <hi>at evening-tide it ſhall be Light.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:38699:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Now a Work ſhortly to each of theſe Things: And now for the firſt which was this, That the <hi>Kirk</hi> may be ſometimes in a Caſe that can neither be Dark nor Clear, neither Dark nor Light, neither Night nor Day; but as it were, ſomewhat in her Caſe that looks Dark like, and ſomewhat in her Caſe that looks Bright and Lightſome like again: This is Propheſied to be in the days of the Goſpel, that in the days of the Goſpel there ſhould be letten out upon the <hi>Kirk,</hi> ſuch a Diſpenſation as this: For this Propheſie hath a reference to the days of the Goſpel. The <hi>Church</hi> of GOD will be ſometimes in that Caſe, when it will not nor cannot be ſaid, that ſhe is altogether Light, nor altogether Dark, nor that it is altogether Night, nor altogether Day with her: But how then? Not Day nor Night, but a mixture of both: Some thing that looks Light like in her Caſe, and ſome thing that looks Dark like in her Caſe. It was ſo with the Church of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in thoſe days, when ſhe was in the Land of <hi>Egypt;</hi> there was ſome thing that look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Dark like in Her Caſe, and ſome thing that looked Light like in Her Caſe; Again ſome thing that looked like GODs forgetting and forſaking of Her, and ſome thing that looked like GODs Remembring and Delivering of Her again. That which looked Lightſome and White like in Her Caſe was this, that the LORD gave Intimation to Moſes <hi>that He had ſeen their Affliction in</hi> Egypt, <hi>and was come down to Deliver them;</hi> And had ſent him Commiſſioner to <hi>Pharaoh</hi> to bid him let the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> go, for he would have them out of the Land of <hi>Egypt</hi> to ſerve Him: That looked Light like, that was Day like in their Caſe, and a White Spot in their Cloud: And there was ſometime they knew this, and had the underſtanding of it, they rejoiced and was glad, and no queſtion praiſed it much, that was White like: But again, that which looked Dark like in their Caſe was this, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of being Delivered out of their Affliction, they have a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:38699:4"/>New Affliction laid on: And <hi>Pharaoh</hi> inſtead of letting them go, he makes their Bondage ſtronger and greater. This look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed very Dark like, and the People grew all Dejected and Heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and they gave no Thanks to GOD for this, nor to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> for his Pains; this looked very Dark like: So it was alſo with the Church in the Days of the New Teſtament, ſome things there that looked very Dark like in Her Caſe, and ſome things looked Light like in it.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Firſt</hi> of all, This looked Dark like in it, that when all the Church that was at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was called, the Honeſt Man <hi>Stephen</hi> was ſtoned, that was to begin the New Teſtament <hi>Kirk</hi> with; that was Dark like: But here ſomething yet, that was Lightſome like with it again, the Miniſters when ſcatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, went every where Preaching the Goſpel, and their Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing had Good Effect upon many for bringing them into JESUS CHRIST: Miniſters was willing to Preach, and People was apt to Hear; ſo that their Out-caſting was their Gathering through GODs Bleſſing; that looks Light like again. So in the time of the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Captivity when the King of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> led the Church of <hi>Iſrael</hi> into Captivity from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that was Dark like; the Temple is all burnt and broken down; the Church and People led into Captivity, Enemies ſet up; the People of GOD overthrown, that looked very Dark like: But this looked ſomewhat Lightſome like again in the Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, that the LORD keeped ſtill ſome Prophets &amp; Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers among them, to point out to them their Duty, and what <hi>Iſrael</hi> ought to do: They were not keeped without Means, for they had the Word and Prophets among them, that was Light like; and withall, it was manifeſted, that at the end of the 70 Years that ſhould be accompliſhed on them at <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> that then they ſhould be brought back again, and enjoy their own Land again, and their former Priviledges; this was White like, as ye may ſee, wherein both their Conditions is
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:38699:4"/>ſet out in that 29. of Jeremiah 10. Verſe. <hi>For thus ſaith the LORD, that after ſeventy years is accompliſhed at Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon I will Viſit you, I will perform my Good Word to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you, in cauſing you to return to this Place.</hi> There was Seventy years that was to be accompliſhed at <hi>Babylon</hi> under Captivity, that was ſad; that was Dark like: but there was a Return to their former Priviledges again after the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty years was accompliſhed; that was Blythſome &amp; Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome like again: They were caſten out of the Kirk that was at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that was ſad: But they were a Kirk among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that was Lightſome like again. They were caſten out of the Church that was at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that was ſad; but they were not caſten out of the Heart and Mind of GOD, that was Light like again; they had the Manifeſtations of His Good Will to bring them back to their former Priviledges, that was Light like.</p>
            <p>Now that we may Apply this to our preſent Caſe, for that is the thing that we ſtand moſt in need of: I ſay for Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, We may apply this to our preſent Caſe; we may ſay it is the preſent Caſe of the Church of <hi>Britain</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> this day; There is ſomething looks very black like in our preſent Diſpenſation; and there is ſomething looks very white like and day like in our preſent Diſpenſation, that is as ſo many white Spots in our Cloud, and is ſomething Day like in the mideſt of our Night. And in the Firſt Room we ſhall ſpeak a word to what is very Black like in our preſent Diſpenſation and there be theſe Black like Tokens in our preſent Caſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The LORD hath taken away His <hi>Ordinances,</hi> that is a very Night like Diſpenſation, a very Black like thing in our Caſe: I aſſure you it is very Dark like. Many of the People of GOD they cannot ſee throw it: It is ſo ſad, that he ſhould have emptied ſo many Congregations at once, is very Dark like.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:38699:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> This is very Dark like in the preſent Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that there is none to own <hi>Zions</hi> Caſe at this Time; all the Great Ones for the moſt part, they paſs by Her Caſe: All our Nobles has turned their back upon GOD and the Kirk, &amp; would command all their Subjects to do ſo likewiſe: And all that would look a warm look to <hi>Zion,</hi> is the butt of their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation; that looks very Dark like, that is a Diſpenſation very Night like. The <hi>Gentiles</hi> has alſo for the moſt part turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their back upon <hi>Zion,</hi> and will own Her with no Help, and will ſhew Her no Compaſſion for Her Comfort, that looks Dark like; That is a very Night like Diſpenſation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> This looks very Dark like in our preſent Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that the People of GOD is ſo full of <hi>Diviſions,</hi> that they cannot have Light together to be of one Mind, in the matter of Sin and Duty; but that which one ſays is Sin, another ſays it is Duty; one Godly Man having a Principle of Godlineſs, ſays ſuch a Thing is a Duty, another Godly Man ſays, na; but it is a Sin: This is very Dark like; This is an Evidence of great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Darkneſs, when we cannot agree in Judgement upon what is Sin, and what is Duty: But one of the People of GOD ſays, ſuch a thing is a Sin: Another ſays, na; but it is a Duty: O ſad that this ſhould be among the Godly, even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Godly themſelves, it is very dark like; it were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing and it were ſo between us and our Enemies; it were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ſee this betwixt the Godly and the Wicked; but to ſee it among the Godly themſelves, it is very ſad and dark like.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> This looks Dark like in our preſent Diſpenſation, that there is ſo much failing and fainting in the Ways of GOD as there are; and ſo great a turning aſide to crocked Paths; and that there are ſo few Valiant for Truth, that is very dark like in the preſent Diſpenſation: This is alſo dark like, that there is none that knows the time how long our darkneſs ſhall continue: There is very few to whom the <hi>LORD</hi> is Reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38699:5"/>any thing of His Mind anent the Delivery of His Work. <hi>He hath hid Himſelf in His Anger. He hath hid Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in His Wrath. He hath ſhut up Himſelf as within a Stone-wall, and will not Reveal any thing of His Mind to us;</hi> that is Dark like. This is alſo very Dark like in the preſent Diſpenſation, that none ſtirs up himſelf to lay hold on Him; and that there is ſo few to ſtand in the Gap to turn away His Wrath. And this is alſo very Dark like, that all our <hi>Publick Ordinances</hi> is gone; ſo likewiſe we have letten all our Privat Meetings go with them: As it were the Rulers by a Wicked Law, hath chaſed us all away from a Part of our Duty, and we have run away from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Part of it unchaſed; They have violently ſhut us away from the <hi>Publick Ordinances,</hi> and we have run away from the Privat Meetings of the People of GOD, and we have not ſtudied to Edify them: As if we were looſed from our Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, when we were ſhut away by a Wicked Law; this looks very Dark like alſo, and is an Evidence of greater Darkneſs, that there is ſo many Faithfull, Able and Honeſt Miniſters taken away by Death at this Time; Some by the LORDs Hand, and that by an ordinary Death; and others, that Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies has Cruelly Executed; and ſo there is many an Uſefull Inſtrument of His Work taken away; which indeed might have been Uſefull Inſtruments, if the LORD had keeped them alive; Each one of them might have been as a Thouſand, and if helped of <hi>GOD,</hi> would have been very Uſefull for a Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Work: And now their being Removed and Taken away, looks very Sad and Dark like, and is very Black like in the preſent Diſpenſation; that the <hi>LORD</hi> (as it were) ſhines u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon all the Deſigns of the Enemy, and Diſcountenances (as it were) any Attempt of His People, that they have for their own Defence; This is very Dark like, that almoſt there is nothing that the Enemies takes in Hand, but it Thrives with
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:38699:6"/>them, and comes to paſs: And nothing that the People of <hi>GOD</hi> takes in Hand as a Mean of Defence, but there are ſome miſlook or other comes upon it; that is very Dark like, that their Attempts and Endeavours Thrives not: It is alſo very Dark like in the preſent Diſpenſation, that there is ſo much Profanity and Atheiſm like to get footing among us: and inſtead of Profeſſing the <hi>Protestant Religion;</hi> Folk is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not Profeſſing it, but they are Denying it: And Folk is not only Falling away from Godlineſs, but Falling away from the Profeſſion of it: And many turning <hi>Popiſh</hi> in our Kirk; This is very Dark and Night like.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Laſtly,</hi> This is very Dark like in the preſent Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation, that the more <hi>GOD</hi> ſtrikes, we are the more har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened; ay the more we are ſmitten, our Hearts is the more hard: All theſe things looks very Dark and Night like upon the Church of <hi>Britain</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> Theſe are very Black Tokens of a Sader and Darker Night: But yet (as I have ſaid before) there is alſo ſome Light like Tokens in theſe Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations of <hi>GOD</hi> towards His People and Church at this Time. So that our Diſpenſations that we meet with at this Time, are made up of Light and Darkneſs: Something of Light, and ſomething of Darkneſs is in the preſent Diſpenſation; that the <hi>Church</hi> in theſe Lands is tryſted with. For as we have many Black like Tokens in our Diſpenſations to make our Hearts ſad; ſo we have ſome Light like Tokens alſo, that is as ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny White Spots in the mideſt of our Cloud that gives us ground of Hope, and I ſhall Name <hi>four</hi> or <hi>five</hi> of them.</p>
            <p>And the Firſt Thing that looks Clear like and is ſome To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for Good, which is a White Spot in the mideſt of our Cloud; The <hi>LORD</hi> is giving His People an Anſwer at this Time, both of their own Prayers, and of many others, that has gone before them that hath died in the <hi>Faith.</hi> I ſay, He is now giving the People of <hi>GOD</hi> an Anſwer of all their Prayers, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:38699:6"/>they never ken of it. What was their Prayers ſay ye? Wa, was not this their Prayers that <hi>GOD</hi> would take ſome Effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al way of Purging of His Houſe, and of making His Inns Clean, &amp; of making Himſelf a Clean Houſe? And now, is He not giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Excellent Anſwer to all theſe our Prayers, though we little Obſerve it? This was the Prayers of the People of <hi>GOD,</hi> and they have now gotten an Anſwer. For <hi>Presbyteries</hi> did but little in this: There was ay ſome Unworthy Miniſters keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in, and <hi>Elders</hi> that ſhould not have been keeped in, and becauſe Formal, and Legal Proceſs could not be gotten againſt them, they were ay keeped in, and not caſten out, and they being keeped in, were ay as Pricks and Thorns in the Fleſh and Sides of the Honeſt Party; and this put them ay to their Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers again, that <hi>GOD</hi> would take ſome Effectual Way to Purge His Houſe. And whether He be Anſwering theſe Prayers or no, Judge ye and ſee. O but He is like now to take ſome Effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual Way to Purge His Houſe of many Naughty <hi>Miniſters</hi> &amp; <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> that otherwiſe would not have been caſten out in haſt; He is doing more for the Purging of His Houſe in one Year now by this preſent Diſpenſation, than could have been down in twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Years by <hi>Presbytery.</hi> This is alſo Light like, that <hi>GOD</hi> is taking ſuch an Effectual Method, and thereby Anſwering the Prayers of the Saints for making to Himſelf a Tight Building a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, thats Light like.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> There is another Thing that looks very Light like, and Day like again in the preſent Diſpenſation, and that is, all thoſe that <hi>GOD</hi> hath brought to the Stage at this time to bear Teſtimony for His Cauſe, they have been helped of Him to carry ſo Honourably for his Cauſe, that they have put Great Reſpect upon it by their Sufferings, and has made it more Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious than ever before: So that He hath made the Cauſe more Glorious by the Suffering of theſe that hath ſuffered for it; than ever they would have made it by their Actions, and they had
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:38699:7"/>lived never ſo long. So that there is more Honour put upon the Cauſe and Work of GOD by the Martyrdom of my Lord <hi>Argyle</hi> and precious Mr <hi>Guthrie,</hi> and ſome others, that they have Baniſhed, nor could have been put upon it by all their Actions, and they had lived never ſo long: This is ſome little White Spot in the mideſt of our Cloud, that Dying and Living, He makes ay His People put Reſpect upon His Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Cauſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> There is ſomething White like in the preſent Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation, that the LORD is ay making that which Enemies are making and deſigning for the utter Ruine of the Work of GOD to put themſelves the further behind, and give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the more adoe: and alſo by conſequence of that to breed ſome more ground of hope to His People, and ſo it contributes to the Advantage of the Low Work of GOD, and has Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced it a great ſtap. There is ſome other Acts that they have put forth againſt His Cauſe and People, hath Advanced the Low Work of GOD a great ſtap, the cruelty of their Deſigns, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed in their Wicked Acts, has done meikle Good to this Work, tho they intended it for Ill: Some of their Acts that they have now put forth, has put ſome Miniſters to the Fields to preach, that if they had not been ſo Cruel, would have ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſtill at home: But now the Cruelty of their Acts hath put them to the Fields to preach, and People to the Fields to hear them, which otherways would have ſitten ſtill in their Neſts, if ſo be their Acts had not been ſo Cruel; Their Acts that way hath done meikle Good to the Cauſe of GOD: For it hath likewiſe bred in the Hearts of the very Profane, a loathing of them and their Way, and a love to the Truth more than before. Their ſending out to Quarter, and Ceſs, and Plunder, hath been ſo far from Advancing of their own Cauſe, though they deſigned it for that end, that it hath brought many of their ſide oft it, that was even almoſt Complyed and Banded with
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:38699:7"/>them, and had a Reſpect to them before this their Cruelty I ſay it hath brought many to turn their back on them, that was Adhering to them, and beginning to Comply with them. This is alſo White like in the preſent Diſpenſation, and is ſome little White Spot in the mideſt of our Cloud, and gives us ground of Hope, that the LORD will ariſe yet with the Light Day of the Goſpel to the poor Church of <hi>Britain</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and that is, that the LORD is beginning to plead the Cauſe of his People that when we are ſhut up, and none left to plead our Cauſe, He is ſaying, that he will plead it Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and in a manner indeed He hath ſaid, <hi>Put up your Sword and I will draw Mine:</hi> He hath ſaid to His People, Put up your Sword, and fylle not your Fingers on them; but I will let you ſee that I will lay them Heaps upon Heaps; I will let you ſee what I will do with the Great Noblemen and Ladies that break my <hi>Covenant</hi> at <hi>London,</hi> that would ſet their feet down upon the LORDs Ground, they could not ſet their Noble Feet upon the LORDs Earth when they went down to the Breach of GODs <hi>Covenant;</hi> but I ſhall gar them (ſays the LORD) be harled to Holes and Dyke-ſides where their Carcaſes ſhall be ſtinking upon the Ground; when the Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus City <hi>London</hi> where all this Miſchief was firſt contrived a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Work of GOD, and the <hi>Covenant</hi> firſt burnt. I ſay all theſe Miſchiefs contrived and acted, GOD hath dung His Sword againſt them (<hi>viz.</hi> by the Viſitation or Plague) and laid them Heaps upon Heaps. GOD hath given His Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple a Seing Mends of them, ſo that they are forſt to pity their Enemies, and ſay alas! alas for them, and Father alas for that, that is come upon them; this is White like and is as a White Spot in our Cloud, and ſays, that GOD will yet Avenge the Quarrel of a broken <hi>Covenant,</hi> for He is beginning to do ſo already.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> We have this to look too which is Clear like in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:38699:8"/>the preſent Diſpenſation, and is a White Spot in the mideſt of our Cloud, and that is, The heinous Perfidelity of the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latical Party;</hi> that ſays, that GOD will be about to be A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged on them: We have this to be a Ground of Hope, that we had even all thoſe Men once in our Day, that is now crying down this Work, and ſpitting upon it (as it were) and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring to get it at under: Theſe Men once in a day cryed it up, as faſt as we do now; They cryed up the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and cryed up the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> and put it up upon others to do ſo, and Suffer for, as well as the Suffering Servants of GOD that are now Suffering for its Doing. I know there is ſome of you in this Pariſh kens ſomething of it, and has been Witneſs to it; that once he that is turned <hi>Prelat</hi> among you, ſwore the <hi>Covenant</hi> before you, and was very forward in it; and in a word, ſpoke als much for it as any other about him; and ſwore you to your <hi>Covenant</hi> at your Sacrament (<hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>James Hamilton</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Galloway</hi>) and then ſhoke his lap, and ſaid, So let GOD ſhake every Man out of his Inheritance that bides not by this <hi>Covenant.</hi> We have this Advantage of all theſe Enemies that they cryed once, and that not long ago up the Work, that we this Day own as faſt as they are now cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it down; and cryed down <hi>Prelacy</hi> as faſt as ever we cryed it down, and does cry it down this Day: But if they hold it as a Principle to be the Right Government of the Church of CHRIST, it had been ſome Manlineſs in them to have cryed it up: But in this they are Beaſted, that they hold ay be that Side that there is moſt outward Advantage in; their Perſidy ſays, that GOD will be avenged on them, and gives His Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ground of Hope: For the laſt Years they cryed down <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy,</hi> and up the Work and Cauſe of GOD as faſt as any Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and then it was but even <hi>Saul</hi> among the Prophets with them: This may be a ground of Hope to us, and a White Spot in our Cloud; Now ſo much for the Doctrine.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:38699:8"/>
            <p>The <hi>Second</hi> Thing we would ſpeak a Word to from the Text, is this, <hi>But it ſhall be one Day, that ſhall be known to the LORD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Dictrine</hi> is that, Though ſometimes the LORD may lengthen out the Trouble of His <hi>Kirk</hi> for a long time, yet there is other times in which it will not be long, but a ſhort time, for <hi>one day,</hi> and that is, <hi>Firſt,</hi> When Enemies Cruelty is ſo great, and they are very Violent; then it ſhall be but for <hi>one day.</hi> Now it is not long that they will Reign, when they are very Cruel and Violent in their Courſe. <hi>Haman</hi> he had one day, a little while, and O but he was Cruel, and the Acts that he made was to the utter overthrow of the Kirk of GOD, and he will have it done all in one day; he will have all done in a little time; no peace and peace, but he will have all done in one day well: Therefore the Kirk hath but <hi>one day</hi> of Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; He will not let her ly under this Tyrany, when Enemies is very Cruel, but preſently gives her an outgate. And ſo at the beginning of the New Teſtament Church, there roſe then a great heat of Perſecution; the honeſt man <hi>Stephen</hi> was ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and a great Perſecution was raiſed, but preſently the LORD gave reſt throughout all the Churches; but giff it was Cruel, the LORD ſuffered it not to be long. That we may apply this to our preſent Caſe and Diſpenſation this day, then it ſayes our Darkneſs will not be long.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> This even ſays it, The great Violence of this Party that is now up, and upon foot; the Violence now uſed by this <hi>Prelatical party</hi> againſt us, that hardly would the like have been uſed by <hi>Turks,</hi> let be by Men of the ſame Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; yet their Acts hath been, and is full of Violence againſt us: What Violence was in that Act in the mideſt of Winter, to put ſo many Families to ſeek their Lodging, and Winter-quarters, and in the midle of Winter to make Deſolate the whole Land from Preaching, that they ſhall not have a Word
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:38699:9"/>ſpoken to them that now ſtands in need of a Word of Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Comfort in the preſent Caſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> There was great Violence that was uſed by them in their taking of the Lives of the Martyrs; what Violence did they uſe againſt them, they were not only content to take their Lives, but they would have the moſt honourable part of their Body, to wit, their Head denyed the honor of a Burial; the like of which was never done to <hi>Proteſtant Miniſters</hi> by <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Ministers</hi> before,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Thoſe that was baniſhed it would not ſatisfie their Humour to give them a months time to provide for Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or ſo long time as was neceſſar for expeding of their Affairs, but preſently commands them to ſail with Violence &amp; Tuke of Drum; ſo that they might neither ſee Wife nor Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, if they came not to them: And then what Cruelty was uſed by them ſinſyne in this Land by Scourging ſome, and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them upon the Cheeks, and then Baniſhment; and I doubt who could expreſs their Fault before ſix Judicious Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors And then what Cruelty was uſed againſt that Faithfull Miniſter (to wit) Mr. <hi>Smith,</hi> in putting him in the Thieves Hole with Irons upon him among Mad-men, and giff ye would know all his Fault, it was even becauſe he would not call the Biſhop <hi>my Lord;</hi> and then becauſe his Friends had acceſs to him there, where they communicated ſomething to him for the Supply of his Neceſſity, they deny him the Priviledge, and put him in another Hole where no acceſs is to be had to him by none of his Friends to come to him and comfort him; this was great Cruelty: This and ſuch like ſays, that their day will not be long Ye know that becauſe Satan was ſhortly to be trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den under foot, therefore he was very Violent; and ſo becauſe GOD has a Party to Deſtroy, when they have accompliſhed their Work; Therefore he gives them leave to tread them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfoot, and to go faſt forward. We thought that the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:38699:9"/>
               <hi>Biſhops</hi> ran faſt till they were in the Pit; yet he gives thir Liberty to put more Work through their Hand in one day, nor the former <hi>Biſhops</hi> would have done in a year: Now this ſpeaks out alſo, that He will not let this Trouble ly long upon His People, leſt they make His People put out their Hand to Iniquity. His People is even ſo ſore put at, and ſo taiſled with them, by ſuch Burdens that they put upon them, that if we think our LORD JESUS CHRIST have a mind to keep His People free of Sin, and keep their Garments Clean at this Time, and bring His People through as we know he will; Then we think He will not let His People continue long under the Trouble; for Enemies is very Cruel. Ye may read their Cruelty in that 51. of Iſaiah 22. chap. 23. verſe, where the Violence of a paralel People is held out; <hi>Thus ſaith the LORD thy GOD that pleadeth the Cauſe of His People, I have taken the Cup of Trembling out of thy Hand, and given it to the Hand of your Enemies, who hath ſaid, bow down the Soul that we may go over.</hi> There the Wrongs they are doing to the People of GOD; It is not their Bodies that will ſatisfie them; but either they will have the Maſtery of their Conſciences or nothing elſe will ſatisfie them. They will ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have their Souls to bow down that they may gang over, or they have no Satisfaction at all. The People of GOD would bear with them, or make leſs din, if it were only their Bodies that they were ſeeking Victory over; but they will have their Conſciences alſo, <hi>they will have their Souls to bow down that they may gang over.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well farther I would make this Uſe of it, If the Churches Affliction laſt but <hi>one day,</hi> becauſe Enemies are very Cruel as ye may ſee them, then labour to bide it out; Many a Man will repent it that he has not bidden out longer; Many a Man will think with himſelf immediatly in the day of their Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, O giff I had ſtayed it out <hi>one day</hi> longer; O giff I had
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:38699:10"/>payed the other Fynd, and bidden the other Streſs and the other Preſsere I had ſtained my Conſcience: I may allude to that word of <hi>Samuels</hi> to <hi>Saul,</hi> ye may ken that <hi>Samuel</hi> ſaid to <hi>Saul</hi> he bides him bide a while from offering a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice till ſeven days were ended; this was the Word of the LORD to him, and then <hi>Samuel</hi> promiſed to be at him; well <hi>Saul</hi> begins to be ſore put at by the <hi>Philiſtins,</hi> and comes under Hardſhips; and ſo he looking for no better of it, he diſobeyed, and or ever the time come, he goes and offers a Sacrifice, as many do when they begin to be ſore preſt and put at, they will Reſolve that they will even Diſobey the Word of GOD a little, and go over the belly of their Light, and croſs their Conſcience, and go over altogether. But well, <hi>Saul</hi> has no ſooner offered the Sacrifice, but als ſoon <hi>Samuel</hi> comes. O Fool thinks he with himſelf giff I had ſtand it out <hi>one day</hi> longer, then it had been well. Could ye not ſtay it out <hi>one day</hi> longer? Can ye not Suffer <hi>a Day</hi> Man? Can ye not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to have the Croſs upon your Back <hi>one day?</hi> What if He had put it to you to bear it all your Days, behoved ye not to have done it, before ye had done Worſe; Will ye not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to bear it <hi>one day? It ſhall be one Day that ſhal be known to the LORD.</hi> O ſay ye, I wad bide it out and I kent how long it would continue; but alas I cannot tell when that day will be. Well ſays the LORD, indeed that is true, I will neither let Friends nor Foes wit of that Day; <hi>But it is a Day known to the LORD:</hi> Let that ſatisfie you; <hi>It is a Day known to Me,</hi> that Loves you as well as ye do your ſelves, and there the Point. The Day of the Kirks Trouble, and how long it will continue, or how ſoon it will end, is a Day that He keeps Secret, and neither Reveals to Friends nor Foes: He will not let Enemies be Diſpoſers of the Kirks Trouble, for then it would laſt too long: He will not let Friends be Diſpoſers of it, for they would take the Short-cut of it, and it would laſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:38699:10"/>too ſhort; <hi>It is a Day known to the LORD:</hi> There is three Things here.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> He knows when it will begin, and hath the diſpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it as to the beginning of it; it cannot begin a Moment ſooner than He hath determined.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> He hath the Diſpoſing of it as to the Darkneſs of it; He kens how many Dark Clouds, and how Thick the Darkneſs will be upon the Kirk. And,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> He kens alſo when it ſhall cloſe, and all the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the World ſhall not get it lengthened one hour, not not a Moment ſhall they lengthen it longer. So I ſay the LORD hath the Continuing and Diſpoſing of the Churches Trouble as to the Timing of it, and as to the Manner of it, and as to the Period and Cloſe of it, and all the World ſhall not get the Church holden a Moment longer in Affliction, although it be always their Deſign. How long think ye <hi>Pharaoh</hi> thought to have keeped <hi>Iſrael</hi> under <hi>Egyptian Bondage?</hi> no doubt even to the End of the World, and I nothing queſtion but they thought ſo themſelves a little before they were delivered, that they would never win out of it; But though the Devil and Enemies of the Kirk of GOD, ſet their Time to be at the End of the World; yet <hi>GOD</hi> hath ſet His Time alſo, and that was not their Time; but it was that ſame Day 400 and 30 Years that they came into <hi>Egypt,</hi> that ſame very Night they March<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of <hi>Egypt;</hi> that ſame very Night was their Bondage done: They might ſtay no longer, that ſame very Night behov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed they to go: Might they not have ſtayed till the Morn? No. Frae the Time was done, they might not ſtay a Moment longer; that ſame very Night they behoved to March.</p>
            <p>Now the Laſt Word is, <hi>at Evening Time it ſhal be Light,</hi> it ſhall be Light, it ſhall be Light, and they had all ſworn the contrary it ſhall be Light; and <hi>Prelats</hi> and <hi>Malignants</hi> would all gather together againſt the Church as a Thick Cloud, yet
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:38699:11"/>it ſhall be Light like, and it ſhall be Light at Evening that is more; that even when Folk will expect or may expect a Dark Hour, then it ſhall be Light at evening time when every Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy will think a Dark Night is coming on them <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So the Note is this, that when moſt Darkneſs is ſuſpected, then immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly the LORD ſhall cauſe Light to ariſe on the Church. There is Two Things we would ſpeak a Word too:</p>
            <p>The <hi>Firſt</hi> is this, That notwithſtanding the Kirk being in great Trouble for a Time, yet She ſhall not continue in it; but it ſhall be Light.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I ſhall ſpeak a Word to this, That it ſhall be Light when it is even at the Darkeſt Hour.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Firſt,</hi> Though the Church be in Darkneſs for a Time, yet She ſhall be Light, Why? Wa GOD is Strong enough to bring Light to the Church in Oppoſition to Poor Pieces of Clay; ſince He has promiſed to make a Lamp always to ſhine before His <hi>Anointed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> It ſhall be Light, for GOD is Wiſe enough to bring Light about to Her, though Men cannot ſee what Way it will come; He is Strong enough and Wiſe enough to bring it about, both in Oppoſition to the Malice of Men and the Wyles of Men; and for Grounds of Comfort to you (that are His People) that He will do ſo, I ſhall give you theſe two.</p>
            <p>And <hi>First</hi> of all, There is ſome Light already in the mideſt of our Darkneſs. <hi>Secondly,</hi> It ſhall be Light; the People of GOD ſhall have Light; <hi>Light ſhall ſhine for the Righteous: The Son of Righteouſneſs ſhall ariſe with Healing under His Wings:</hi> For He hath made all His Friends within theſe Lands to look for Light; they are all made to hope for Light, and lippens for it; this is their Expectation Dying and Living; this they live in the hope of, and this they Dye in the Faith of, becauſe He hath ſaid, <hi>the Expectation of the Poor ſhall not periſh,</hi> Pſalms 9.18. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It ſhall be Light in this
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:38699:11"/>Generation, becauſe if no more Light would ariſe upon us, this would be a great Diſcouragement for People in another Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration that owns GOD and His Way, when it grew Dark with them, and a Cloud fell upon them; it grew Dark with you Generation (ſay they) and they wan never out of it; they wan never from under the Cloud, and ſo we think neither will we: This would put them out of all hope of all Recovery of Light any more. Hence now ſince He has His People to bring throw many Various Troubles, one after another, and hath Truth to Convoy them from one Generation to another, and His People to bear up that Way: There though it were not for our ſakes, yet for the Generation to come, that they may not be utterly Diſcouraged when a Cloud and Darkneſs falls on them: Therefore He will have Light to ariſe upon us; <hi>It ſhall be Light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> It ſhall be Light: There is this Ground for it, the LORD is putting ſome moe Spirits in His Miniſters and People than before. He is beginning to Work ſome more Light and Life at the Hearts of His People; Though it is true, we are all far from the Thing that we ſhould beat; yet ſome Miniſters has more Heart to Venture to Preach, and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple has more Heart to Venture to Hear nor they had before: This ſays <hi>it ſhall be Light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But next, <hi>at Evening it ſhall be Light;</hi> It ſhall not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be <hi>Light,</hi> but it ſhall be <hi>Light at the Evening;</hi> that is, when the greateſt Darkneſs is looked for: There the Point; The Church and People of GOD is never nearer hand a Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very and Day-light, then when it is Darkeſt; The Church of GOD is never nearer hand Day-light, then when it is Darkeſt with Her: When in all Human Appearance there is ay a Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and Darker-night coming, that is ay a great Evidence of drawing near to the Light. <hi>Iſrael</hi> Light in <hi>Egypt</hi> came when in all Mens Eyes it ſeemed to grow Darker, for their Bondage
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:38699:12"/>and Slavery is made greater, their Task doubled; they are put to Impoſſibilities, they are forbidden to have Straw given them, and yet to fulfill the Teal of their Brick; They are put to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibilities, and when put to Impoſſibilities, then it grows Light. And if ye would ſpear-when the Church in theſe Lands will be Delivered, it will be ſhortly after Miniſters and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are put to Impoſſibilities; and is there not ſomething of that come forth already in ſome of their Acts, wherein Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are charged to Flit Twenty Miles from their own Pariſh-Kirk, and many ſuch Acts which are like that, which the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was put to in <hi>Egypt,</hi> which was Impoſſibilities; <hi>Go get you Straw, yet fulfill the Peal of your Brick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well then when it is Darker nor ever it was before, then gather ye the more Hope from it, that ſhortly it ſhall be Light; ay the Darker it grow, gather the more Hope of Light; ay when there comes an New Act forth more Severe and Crueller than the former, then bleſs GOD for that; your Delivery is nearer than before, that is ay a New Token of Light: <hi>At Evening it ſhall be Light,</hi> That is a New Token that Light is not far off. Indeed if ye look upon Things by Human Reaſon, ye will plead your ſelves out; but we muſt plead by GODs Word and Promiſe, and that Way we will plead our ſelves in: For that is contrare to Human Reaſon, <hi>that at Evening it ſhall be Light.</hi> O ſay ye we were never ſo ſore put at as we are now; we were never ſo Streſſed and Preſſed as we are now: It may be ye in this Place has not met with it yet; but <hi>Gallo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way</hi> and the <hi>West</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> has met with it: Well, when this comes to your Door that ye are ſo ſore put at, wa all the better of that, it is a Token of Delivery, <hi>at Evening it ſhall be Light.</hi> I ſhall ſay no more, the LORD bleſs what hath been ſpoken unto you.</p>
            <closer>
               <hi>Let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:38699:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
